Check my geese control.
No geese. How about that?
Looks like they have new feces. Oh, none
of the Okay, cool.
All right. What a way to start the
video. Um
All right. So,
uh
basically, um I forgot what I was
leaving off there. What we want to do is
is you want to iteratively build this
script. So you're going to calculate one
score at a time or one set of scores at
a time and then you'll hold those in
memory. So but you'll also write them to
the sheet for auditing, right? So when
we calculate the location scores first,
you're going to write them in the sheet
as a as a step, right? But you're also
you're not going to go back and then
reference the sheet and pull that data
back in because every time you calculate
from the top, it should run all the
calculations again. So you're when you
write to the sheet, you're just saying
this is what we got here. And that helps
us audit it later, but you'll then take
those location scores and keep them in
memory um for the next operation and and
so on and so forth. Uh, so that's just
kind of a point I want to illustrate is
that you don't want to be as you you
don't want to write this all at once and
you don't want to um
you don't want to to to write something
and then have to go reference it to to
know what it is because you should be uh
handling all of these calculations step
by step by step by step in one
operation. But you are writing them out
to different areas for different scores.
And that's like a log or an audit of
what's going on. Um, so, uh, I need to
see a sheet you got currently with data
in it. Um,
let me send you the Tampa one.
Okay, sounds good.
Okay. And then what I'm going to do
is I'm going to create a new sheet.
Sheets new
just so we can get this organized.
Uh
rank whoops
score calculator. And eventually we will
merge the operations right from the one
you've written and and the one we're
about to work on.
Um
so
you've got ranking position ranking URL.
Oh, a lot of interesting areas here
where
he's not ranking so hot. There's an
Orlando raccoon one here. That's odd.
Definitely room for improvement.
A lot of wildlife questions here.
Um, so what I'm not seeing is you got
these sets here which are useful to
generate these, but I'm not seeing these
lined up on that other set, which I
would want to see just because
it's going to help you know how to
target the right My gosh, what is going
on?
It's going to help you know how to
target the right um
what I say going to help you know where
to target the right uh row when you want
to write and submit um some new stuff.
Right? So it looks like you're you're
dumping your results here, but I'm not
seeing a service geo keyword keyword
geo. I'm just seeing the keyword, which
is
sort of a different piece of the
operation, right? Um,
so what I want to see is something like
this,
but this is not just this is like
service level stuff. I guess this is
like your reference sheet for
for your ranking URLs, right? Um,
so let's go into here.
Oh, Gordon, can you share your screen?
Uh,
sorry.
So, what I really want to see
is this list.
We don't necessarily need the latitude,
longitude, though I think we can grab
them.
So, we're going to call this rankings,
right?
There's that.
And I'm going to come over here
and get the results, right? And these
should, I'm assuming, match up.
I think these raw responses are are kind
of what's killing it.
Yeah, I just clicked that like a minute
ago.
Come on. There we go. Good lord.
All right. And then we're going to come
here and we'll just assume it's
something like Oh [ __ ]
The hell happened? It took it It took so
long to copy that it actually pasted the
old thing and now it's not loading.
It's the raw responses. I think
Yeah, I think so, too.
Is it doing that to you? Uh, no not
really. I mean, it's responding good in
my end.
Come on now.
Just going to hit copy again.
And then I'm going to try to paste this.
There we go.
All right. So, you got a ranking
position ranking URL, right? So, few
different things going on here. Now, we
got to do our um
niche
location.
And then I think there's like a keyword
one as well, right? because it's
kind of like that.
And then I think we'll also have a
config at some level.
Come on.
So, several sheets here. You got your
rankings as your set already loaded in
like that.
So then you're going to go back here to
Tampa ranking and you're going to go to
locations
and you're going to grab uh your your
different areas, right? Like all this
information
here.
And you're going to come over to
location.
Paste that in. Oops. We need a column.
There.
Now, I'm unopinionated about the column
names themselves,
but we will make a You said income,
population, and then you did a manual
check.
Yeah, I just had to make sure that uh
what my automation is giving me is uh
accurate.
Okay. And is it like did you find uh
completely accurate or were there
discrepancies?
They're they're accurate. Yeah.
Okay, great. So, what I'm I'm actually
just going to delete these two columns
because I'm just assuming you're you're
correct in your numbers.
Yeah.
Um I don't want to I don't want to
pollute what we've got going on here.
Right. So, then we have to do a location
score.
And again, I could write this um
uh
write this function myself, but
basically what we're going to do is
calculate that score. is going to be a
um
a set of keywords. We come back here and
grab our keywords.
So, this should be
your
services and keywords essentially,
right?
like that.
And then you've got your operation to
generate those um
keyword plus geos which we've already
got like kind of in our
uh these are like the core keywords.
They are
formatted
in the sort of old way, right? Which is
that they're capitalized. Um I'd rather
them
basically remain formatted like this. Uh
I guess these must have come from the
surges or something.
Yeah.
During our process with that because we
were also I think part of the
capitalization was that we were
preparing like title names and stuff. Um
so we were avoiding that. What?
Sorry about that.
Uh so
I think we so so one of the things that
we have to keep in mind um and one of
the reasons I like
this here uh
interesting how these calculated it
right because this is a core keyword. So
basically one of the things we have to
do and we're very concerned with is when
you're looking at your rankings, you
want to know whether the keyword plus
geo is a pure keyword or if it's a um a
location modified one. Right? So in this
case you can see that this one is uh a
pure keyword and this one is location
modified. This one's location modified.
This one's a pure keyword. This one's
location modified. This one's location
modified, right? So, how do you
determine that
from a data perspective?
Um,
when you're analyzing this sheet,
well, it contains the uh like a location
like an area.
That's hard to to do. I would actually
just say, does this match keyword, do
these two match? They need to be uh
controlled for capitalization.
But you want like you'd be able to say
wildlife pest control, wildlife pest
control. That's a match. Wildlife pest
control, wildlife pest control
riverview, not a match, right? So they
have to be like an exact match when
controlled for um per uh capitalization,
right? So that's an easy way for you to
determine if you're working with a core
keyword or if you're working with a
location modified keyword because in our
mindset here and part of this decay
we're talking about that we're trying to
focus on is there is an inherent belief
at least on my end that the raw keyword
is worth more than location modified
keyword because of search volume
generally right people are more likely
to search raccoon removal than raccoon
removal Detroit uh because it's they're
assuming they're going to get some
location aspect to that response. Now,
they might then make that, you know,
search as well. Could be. I can't
necessarily say that the volume is going
to be one way or the other. This is why
we're going to create a
um
a sort of weighted method to be able to
discriminate. Uh so um the interesting
thing about algorithms
uh is that they are sort of these
opinionated guesses about data
relationships and why they matter.
Right? So our big opinion in this above
all things other than location specific
stuff which is more straightforward
because that's about population and and
monetary value within that market. um
which is a pretty safe opinion I think
because you can't make dollar bills come
out of the earth essentially. Uh the
other opinion we're going to take is
that the um base keyword in a market is
worth more than the uh location modified
ones. Partly because the base keyword is
a very singular and then the location
modified is very buried, right? because
there's multip multiplication happening
in in their creation. In this case, it's
only times two, but in other cases, it
might be um more uh
so um
what am I thinking here?
Uh
damn, my brain just turned off. Um,
it was one of the people asking for a
goose dog. The guy in Fort Worth was is
like saying, "You have any goose dogs?
Your mom?"
And she doesn't have any yet. So, um,
what was I going to say? Uh,
sorry, my daughter's also crying, so
that's not helping either.
Um,
where were we? Where did we leave off?
uh you were uh saying uh weighing of
pure keywords and uh
right so that's an opinion we're taking
too is that the the pure keywords are
work and should be considered as a chunk
that is separate from the location ones
because the location ones are um
probably is as I guess handled less
frequently um but also uh the assumption
is that they there's going to be more of
them than there are of the pure keywords
just because of um the the
multiplication aspect and how they're
generated. So if you're allowing the
number of keywords to happen, uh the the
pure keywords are always going to be
outweighed by the the keyword geos
because they multiply. And so if they're
if we're talking about shares of number
of keywords, then you're polluting your
data that way. Now, we're taking an
opinion that they're treated at least
differently. We're not saying that one
has to be worth more than the other uh
necessarily. Um we do in our logarithmic
decay place at the the front end of that
the the um the pure keywords or core
keywords assuming that they have more
value. If it we'd have to treat it
differently if we didn't know. But we
are allowing or we're going to create a
value that allows us to do a slider
right um for where that happens. like
where is this cut off point? So if you
got a logarithmic scale and you're
partitioning it into two pieces to say
that one piece is going to be keyword
plus geo and the other one's just pure
keyword. Drawing that partition point is
going to be a parameter that we feed
into the equation. Right? So we could
say the only the top 10% are pure
keywords and the rest are 90. uh or we
could say the core keywords are worth
80% and then the last 20% are um
geomodified keywords, right? So we get
the ability to really screw with the
output by changing one number which is
something called uh like abstraction,
right? It's creating an interface for a
user to make very minimal inputs to have
drastic I wouldn't say drastic changes
but um valuable changes, right? they
don't have to go into the code and
rewrite how the code functions because
they can just change one parameter and
get it to move significantly. So that is
one parameter we're going to feed from
our config is basically this like uh
partition point in the the that graph of
like on the x-axis like where do we put
that you know should the first
uh 50% be this or that and then um there
is another point there too that we'll
issue at the same time called the kappa
and the kappa determines the slope of
the curve. If the cap is at one then
then it's a straight line and if it's
higher than one then it starts to do
this curving motion right so we can we
can make it a flat treatment right
generally um or or have like a linear
descent uh by setting it at one I think
if we do it even less than that then it
even probably does this and maybe comes
to uh some kind of
point I'm not exactly sure what happens
when you go under one um but we will
have a kappa and we will have uh a
partition point basically uh along the
x-axis. Um and so those are the big
deals. Then inside those what we're
doing is saying all right we've got
we're looking at these by location right
so let's let's take a look at the top
calculation because I think it's
important to understand
uh things from the top well one concept
otherwise first I want to bring in here
um have have you ever heard of
normalization before
I've heard of the term I'm not really
sure what it's for
so normalization is basically taking a
range of numbers numbers that exist,
right? Because they they could apply to
any scenario, right? In some
measurements, you're going to have a
value starting at let's say it's
temperature, right? Like zero Kelvin up
to, you know, whatever Celsius, it's
different. It starts it goes all the way
into the negatives and and you know what
I mean? Like there's different ways of
of calculating like the same thing um
with a with a certain range. To
normalize means that you're creating a
standard scale for all things in the set
to exist between usually zero and one,
but also sometimes negative one and one.
So you're you're probably like, okay,
well, how does that help? Um it helps in
factoring things like mult by
multiplying numbers together because it
allows you to kind of get everything in
the same uh sort of wheelhouse so that
the the calculations are standard and
consistent. An easy way to think of this
is that we could create a normalized
value for a date and we would do that by
you know you've got 365 days in the
year. October 30th is um let's just
Google it, right? How many days into the
year is October 30th?
We'll say 30.
I don't trust the AI answer.
That's going to be [ __ ]
Day of the year calculator
303 days into the year, right? So what
that means is that if you're going to
calculate a normalized score, you would
do 303 divided by 365.
And if we were to just kind of do that
over here in the config and we said 303
/ 365.
Oh, it doesn't want to do the
calculation.
How do you
Why are you treating it like a string?
That's odd.
We'll just do 303
365. Oh, I think I know why. Equals this
divided by that. And that's a normalized
score. You are 83 01369863
through the year. Right? So, you can see
how once you get to 365, you're getting
to a score of one. And on January 1st,
you're at a score of zero. Right. So
that's like a a quick illustration of
like how you get those numbers is not
that complicated. You're usually just
saying like well what is it as part of
the whole if we were to divide the
highest possible value um or divide the
number we're looking at by the highest
possible value what do we get? Right?
So we need a normalization range for
what we're talking about here. Uh the
way that this is logically going to flow
from the top is all about location,
right? because uh it doesn't matter what
a raccoon removal job versus a rat
removal job is worth if there are no
people with no money, right? And that's
what location factors, right? So, um
what we're going to do is we're going to
think about a very specific calculation
um which is going to be this uh the one
that you you were doing before, which is
the the income times the population.
We're gonna make a small adjustment to
the income by subtracting like $32,000
basically from it, which is the poverty
like line, right? So, what you'll do on
that first one for Houston is you'll
take the income minus the the uh the
poverty level to get discretionary
income. And then we're going to multiply
that by the uh um population. And that's
going to give us a number. And we're
going to do that for every single row.
And then we're going to take all of
those together and add them up. And
that's going to be our value of one. So
then we can get our our partial score uh
against all of these guys by dividing
their individual score by the total
number and that'll give us that like 0,
you know, 1 2 4 56 or whatever, right?
And that'll be our location score. So I
can show you a quick equation for that.
uh and we can run it on the sheet but
you will be writing it and running it in
code because it is something that should
happen when you click the button right
you don't want to you want to derive it
from the raw data you don't want to be
pulling the values from the sheet if you
recall correctly um but I can I can
quickly illustrate what that looks like
so uh we'll call this the score this is
actually hard to calculate without two
columns and this is another reason why
you're using the script so we're going
to call this the um we'll call this the
phase one score
or I would say numerical score and we'll
call this the normalized score.
Okay. So then we're going to say um
equals
this
minus
32,000.
Generally, we're going to put it in
parenthesis
and then we're going to multiply it by
the population,
right? That's not a small number.
And then you can see how hard it would
be to deal with this because it's
insane, right?
Um, so then you'd pull this down
and then you would say, uh,
we could calculate the the just a quick
little note here. So we don't have to do
a bunch of calcs. We could just say, um,
total
numerical
and that's going to equal the sum
of this through this.
Right. And then you're going to say this
equals this divided by this. But we're
going to take this and turn we're going
to use these uh Whoops. We're going to
put the dollar signs on the I2 so it
never changes position as we drag it
down. And now you see
very interestingly
these are the numbers you were looking
at before.
Riverview is 0.08.
Rather interesting, right?
And then these should all sum up to one.
Yeah. See how they all add up to one?
Right.
Cool, isn't it?
Yeah.
So then this normalized score is how we
associate what matters most for um for
everything. Now there's an assumption
baked in here that these populations
never intersect with other populations.
We don't really have a good way of
controlling for that. You know what I
mean? You wouldn't you wouldn't really
unless you did like a county level
like analysis as opposed to cities.
However, we're just going to do our best
here. So, it it we're assuming that
there's some level of duplication of
counts going on on like Newport Richie
and Newport Richie East might be not be
the same piece or they may be they may
overlap and so therefore some people are
counted twice. What are you going to do?
Uh we're just looking for general
relative accuracy and not like atomic
accuracy. So it's less of a big deal. Um
so then
the what you can see off of these is
that they do filter down in terms of
importance. Something like Separ is
worth far less to us to rank well in
than something like St. Petersburg which
is actually getting a 0.1. I don't see
any other 0.1s here. Almost everything
else has got a zero.
You know what I mean,
right?
Is Tampa on the list?
I don't see Tampa on the list.
Those are just I think the uh
neighborhood.
Make sure the core location is also
included in your calculations in in your
searches, right? Um because that's going
to be a big population zone and we'll
throw your numbers off. But St.
Petersburg clearly has a big population
and a decent income. It's not too bad.
Uh so there's definitely some money to
go around and this is a good one to
target. Right. We we're already getting
insights
on that stuff. Um some of these other
ones aren't so bad either. A point4 not
so bad. Decent income kind of high
population, right? So there's potential.
Um, now
we got a total numerical. We got the
normalized score. So now the way to
think about this is we'll go over to a
mind node or mind map here.
It opening up. What's going on?
Let's create a new one.
So, you're going to talk about um sort
of total potential score,
which is going to equal one. And then
let's let's look at three locations,
right?
So, we're going to say Riverview is 0088
0.088 088.
No, not what I wanted to do.
We'll just use a couple as an example.
Trinity
20.
Let's get rid of
And then we'll do one more, right? Which
will be
something really bad. Odessa.
So you can see immediately that Odessa
is like worth 10% of what Riverviews
were, right?
which is kind of crazy. It's actually 11
less than 10%.
Um,
so you know that that kind of gives you
a lot of insight on what to target. Like
any effort you put into Odessa is worth
a tenth of what it is into Riverview. So
that's a good calculation for us and why
we're calculating this score at this
stage because it matters to us. And then
we're going to dovtail into sort of like
the uh services calculation, right? So
the services themselves are worth
different things. Um this is calculated
and if you if you recognize
this sort of set of columns is exactly
what we did in the uh in the Google ads
keyword planner. We we just took took a
couple figures. We like found the mean
and we multiplied it by the population.
Same thing, right? Like what is the the
cost per click of this keyword for this?
And then we had an analysis chart where
we were like, let's check bat. What is
bat worth as a share of the market? What
is this worth as a share of the market?
What is that worth as a share of the
market? Um and uh basically created a um
a calculus for you know like what to
focus on right uh in terms of like
keywords and the share of market and
stuff. um and also help us rank order in
our keywords. So what you would want to
do then is per service find that number
where you would go into the keyword
planner and that market. You'd say,
"Okay, we're going to get all the
raccoon ones and and then you'll you'll
try to find every raccoon keyword and
then add up that that value of the share
of market, right?" Um so that'll tell
you, you know, it might be 111 or 14 or
something like that. And then you would
take that and put that into a um
what is it? We'll call it the niche.
You're going to have the niche.
You're going to have the service and
then you're going to have the uh keyword
planner score
keyword.
And then you would do a numerical or you
would you would basically do a
normalization of that. Right? So you
might not be tracking all of the
services that you have in that set. So
let's say we're not focusing on RAT
right now, which is going to be a pretty
big part of any uh any calculation from
the keyword planner. If you're including
RAT in keyword planner, it's going to
make everything else look anemic, right?
So, um, you have to go for,
uh,
let's see, trying to think, my brain is
turning off again. Um, basically, you
want to pull their their normalized
scores from that, put them in this, and
then renormalize them against their own
axis so that you're not including RAT if
you don't want to factor RAT because
otherwise it'll skew your calculations
quite a bit. Um, you can add RAT in
later, and then that'll sort of tip over
the milk cart because it really does
change things. But having created the
right format, all you have to do is add
rat and change it and it won't change
like everything else if you know what I
mean. Um, so uh that's that. And then
the other implicit score here uh I I'll
let you fill these in um and then make
the normalization.
Do you if if I were to say, you know,
raccoon,
squirrel,
bat,
etc. And I were to have, you know, score
of 0.15
uh 0.08.
These are obviously not very high. And
then we'll say this one's 0.12.
You would basically sum those the same
way like we did on the other set. What
are you kidding me?
4.
And then you would you would divide this
by this.
And then you see how we get the
normalized scores again.
So they sort of get resuscitated from
from being low scores in the other
context, if that makes sense. And then
these are the scores we're working with.
So, what you would notice is that your
services are um
you know, you got your bat, raccoon,
squirrel.
You know, again, just as an example,
you'd be taking these numbers and
factoring them here.
So, this gives you your location
and then generally your niche, right? Uh
because all we're doing with the
keywords is rank ordering them. Um they
in my mind they don't matter so much. It
kind of comes down more to the uh
there's a few different ways to handle
it, right? You could
you could do a decay function on the
actual keyword list order for the core
keywords if you wanted. I decided to
just take an average so that you get the
chunk and then you just say we got five
keywords, they're all worth oneif of
whatever that first partition is worth.
Um because I I just don't see a huge
difference in raccoon removal and
raccoon control necessarily. You know
what I mean? Um, maybe there is, maybe
there isn't. Hard to tell. Uh, I think
that if you really wanted to to get
super analytical about it, you'd dive
deeper into that keyword planner data,
but I want something that's robust
enough to work for uh a small market,
right? So, I don't want to be too
opinionated about the actual search term
because you might be missing search
terms because the keyword data from the
keyword planner too sparse to properly
plan for mobile. You know what I mean?
Um, so uh
yeah, that's generally the idea. Um
so you can see that
this is like a filter like a power
filter out of one possible total
riverview is worth this and then it gets
split up that 088 gets split up like
this accordingly based on the niche
right so then based off of whatever um
this is times this right because you
multiply these Uh so if we were to say
just again on this rank score thing, if
we were to say raccoon uh service in
Riverview,
we would calculate a score and the score
would be this number times this number.
So 0.088
times this number that would be equals
this times this
it would be worth like a 0.03 03, right?
I think that's right.
Maybe it's divided by
Hold on.
Oh, that's correct. Yeah, because it's a
fraction of this. That makes sense. 0.03
777. Okay. Yeah, because again, this
would equal one when when the others are
composed together. So that means that
all raccoon keywords are all going to be
taking a share of this score if that
makes sense. And you've got in your
rankings
raccoon control and riverview is going
to be this many keywords like that. So
you could say um
that they're all equally weighted and
they all take an equal share. But we do
want to weight these
core keywords a little differently.
Actually, there's more here, right?
Raccoon removal near me, right? Those
ones. So we know that
amongst those there are core keywords
and there are um the uh geo keywords
and we're going to factor those as a
share by whatever we set this in the
config the um we'll call it the
I got to look at chatbt and and figure
out what we were calling it.
There's a kappa value and a uh
what's it called here? a split
call the partition split
and that's going to be between 0 and
one. So if we were to say 0
uh six six that means that the
everything between zero and 66 is
basically a score band that we would
consider um the core keywords and then
everything 66 and up to one which is 044
would be uh the share that's calculated
for the core keyword and then we would
have a kappa value and we would set the
kappa at maybe five or something to to
generate. Usually you'd be setting at
one for that straight line. Um, which we
could do for now and then we could test
the capillator, right? And change it
around. Not too big a deal. So, um, that
means those those first five keywords
share 66% of the total possible score in
terms of that area on a linear axis. And
if you were to increase the cappa then
this would only that that potential
would only increase. Uh how you doing?
Are you lost yet?
Still following.
Okay, good. Um so I've got the formula
like I I already had this written uh
because I figured I was going to like
throw it at you and then I didn't really
want to like
overwhelm you with it because it might
be kind of crazy. Um but you can see
here that we're adding these parameters
in right so you got a param which was
the number split which is that first one
we had which is a split point between
zero and one IG eg66
then you're just going to give it a list
of core keywords and a list of geo
keywords. So that's going to be you're
going to do a quick analysis on the
sheet only on Riverview, right? Let's
just only focus on this one thing
because you want to you want to compute
these in their own chunks. You don't
want to calculate Riverview and another
one at the same time because you're
trying to you're trying to divide up
shares and so you know that location is
like your big domain. So you don't want
to be crossing over locations and and
calculating shares for keywords in
Riverview against shares and other other
pieces because they they're irrespective
of each other if that makes sense. Um so
when you build this and you calculate
scores, you want to go location by
location, service by service,
location being first, then do service,
service, service. But you'll be doing
keyword calculations, right? So um when
you come down here, you got your core
keywords and your geo keywords. Let's go
back to the script so you can see the
logic in here. Um, so you're adding a
string of core keywords and you're
adding a string of geo keywords. Those
are literally just the actual values of
the keyword itself.
So it'll be wildlife pest control,
wildlife. We're talking about raccoons.
So you'd be doing your core keywords
would be raccoon removal, raccoon
trappers, raccoon removal.
Oh, it's a different it's spelled
differently. Oh, with one Z. Okay, good.
And then raccoon removal near me and
raccoon removal from attic. Right? So
you got five core keywords. You're
matching them against these. That's how
you develop that list. And then you've
got your your list of the location
modified. So that's your raccoon removal
riverview, your riverview raccoon
removal. So that's a list of like 10 and
the other one's a list of five. And they
are quite literally um
given to you.
Uh you're you're giving them the actual
string because the output object is
going to look like
um let me pull up a new
the output object is going to look like
you know raccoon removal
and it's going to say you know 0.01234
01 23 4 five or whatever, right? And
then you're going to have a comma and
it's just going to be this this list
that comes back of all of those
keywords. There'll be 15 of these
including the location modified, right?
Um, and then you'll you will go when
you're writing back to the sheet, you
will go look up riverview
uh and then you look up the the actual
keyword plus geo to find the row, right?
So, you're going to come in here. You're
going to search
basically through this entire list or
whatever. Actually, we're going to do it
over here because this is the cleaner
cleaner one. You're going to come here
and you're going to look for only
Riverview. And then you're going to go
look for keyword plus geo equals raccoon
removal. And then we're going to go into
that column and write the the um the
actual keyword score, which we'll we'll
add here.
And then of course we're going to have
one later for the ranking score which is
like a final step right. So you
basically produce an object from this
calculation. The script will do that for
you where it'll it'll make that output
object and it should give you the right
value. I have not tested it. It is not
very long. Right? That's the beauty of
you know math that makes sense and works
well. Right.
Um, and then of course it has a little a
little test here. I don't really know
how it's making it go. It's creating an
array from length 60. This is the thing
I don't understand. Like what are you
guys doing? Uh, I think it was just
trying to cheaply generate geo keywords
off of this. Um, as an example, uh, but
you can see that literally this is the
type of thing it's looking for with
keywords. It should be very easy to get
for you, right? Um, so that process will
write us out when you're when you're
factoring these inputs correctly. Um,
you're going to get a keyword score. Uh,
the only thing I think we're missing
here is that
we do keyword score.
Hold on. And then we got to multiply it
by
uh
I got to add this in. say, "Hey, for the
script, uh, we need to add in a param
to multiply
the uh
the keyword scores by a single location
um score
or location service score, right?
because we're having to do this times
this.
Actually, I don't think it
is required at that level. Hold on.
There's just a step where these things
get factored, right? Um, so I'm just
trying to figure out
whether we should bake that into this
script or keep it separate and handle it
at the end.
uh is actually a good engineering
question.
So we could permute a
well the geo scores are always going to
be I think you want to do it at this
step because the geo scores are always
going to be um a factor of
uh
that basically they'd always be the same
if you weren't
factoring um
Actually, this is a good good question
and I might have to think about it a
little bit more.
Um, but the the question is usually like
if you're creating all these scores at
the end of the day when you look at one
of those weird math equations, it's just
saying we're going to take this score
and we're going to multiply it by this
score and then we're going to add this
score and then we're going to divide
them all by this score. Right? That's
usually what you're looking at even
though it's all crazy letters and
numbers and stuff. Um so the then the
question becomes um do we want to as
this progresses be making those
calculations or do we want to take
produce a list of scores um then produce
a list of modified scores then produce a
list of like fully rank qualified
scores. Um, and I kind of want to
I kind of want to keep the keyword score
um as brain dead as possible. So, it it
means that we're going to be doing a lot
of calculations
uh
specifically.
Yeah, that's fine. I don't mind handling
them in layers.
So, we won't worry about pushing a
location and niche score in there
because we're just going to do that all
at the end in our uh in our rank
calculation. It means we're going to add
a third column. Basically,
we're going to have our um keyword
score, our rank modifier, um and then a
final score. And the final score is
going to be everything zipped up. Uh,
and then that'll be the number we use
for the keyword itself to say, okay,
this keyword in Riverview is worth this
at this rank, right? If we're ranked
number one, we get this boost. Um, so
that's all we do. So, you got a keyword
score, rank modifier score,
and then a final score.
So the final score,
the the rank modifier score is just
going to be a measure of how we want to
handle um
we'll say uh rank modification kappa.
Let's do the same thing.
So the way I want to handle um the kappa
is the same thing, right? Where it does
like the linear. So, we're going to
actually put this at like a a 10, I
guess. Um, where we know the first one
is worth a lot and the second one is
worth way less but still worth more than
the rest. And then as you get further
out to 10, they're just like worth
almost nothing, right? And, um, I don't
think the 10 has anything to do with the
actual rank we're checking. Um,
but what I'm thinking is
if you if you see a ranking above 10,
you're just basically counting it as
worth nothing, right? So, this this 12
would be a zero effectively. Um, I'm
kind of curious. Road control squirrels.
He's not doing too bad there. Um,
even here, he seems a little weak on
squirrel. Squirrel
removal
pretty good. Squirrel pest removal.
Using words like pest exterminator
definitely weaker but still not bad. You
know what I mean? Like he's ranked four
or five. Could be worse. What were the
What's Riverview's worth? 0088. I want
to say St. Petersburg.
That was the big one, right?
Let's go check St. Petersburg.
St. Peters.
What the hell?
I'm getting too excited here. Wow. St.
Petersburg seems to be ranking quite a
bit over in Trinity.
Not great though. Look at those
rankings. Aren't very good. Temple
Terrace. There we go.
A lot of ones, threes, twos.
We could get these raccoons higher would
be a big boost for him.
Not bad overall in St. Petersburg for it
being worth so much.
Did we do a surge over there?
Uh yeah, I think we did uh one for St.
Petersburg.
Aha.
Look at those results, baby.
So yeah, I'm actually quite pleased with
that because you know, you you look at
this and you're like, man, St.
Petersburg is worth so much and then
we're just slapping it over there. So
this gives you really good if the surge
is effective in what it does. This gives
you a really good target list for surges
so you're not wasting time. You know
what I mean,
right?
Um which is quite cool because you can
have an impact for sure. Uh so where
were we? Uh raccoon.
Uh all right. So we were going to
calculate these scores, right? So
in the rank score, sorry, I know this is
taking a while, but I'm hoping to kind
of get some of this across because I I
want to give you enough that you can
start working this
um and and deal with these pieces. Uh
let's go back to I think this is it. We
are we are actually here. So you got a
keyword score, a rank modifier score. We
already talked about how to calculate
that. It's basically this formula. The
challenge you're going to have is and
I'll give you this right now.
Copy this code. I'll even share the chat
with you if it's useful.
Copy the link. See if you can see this.
All right.
I want to try checking this in a
different browser.
Yeah, chat open.
Interesting.
Should check and see if uh we can get
links out from this
cuz I'm not logged in. You see that?
Yeah.
That would be a good experiment. See if
you can't um get it to put links in.
You to go uh get it to write an entire
article about squirrel removal and say,
"Hey, uh can you tell me what the um
squirrel removal
page URL is for AAAC wildlife removal
of Tampa?
There's a link out here. Source here.
Share chat.
Copy link.
Go over here.
Paste this in. Sorry, I'm getting on a
tangent.
Inspect element.
Maybe the page source isn't the right
one. Inspect element.
Oh, it tries to take you off page.
Interesting.
Yeah. I wonder if this uh stops it from
being worthwhile.
I have to assume we would have heard
about this if uh it was so easy.
Yeah.
But always something worth testing,
right? Um anyway uh
so
we calculate
the the keyword score which is just that
um that analysis right of the uh
the full potential of those things. And
this what you'll notice when you do this
is that they'll repeat, right?
Like wildlife pest control is always
going to be worth the same keyword score
regardless of location and so are these
other terms.
If we're if we're not multiplying that
other number there,
um then those keywords are going to be
work uh
what is it? [ __ ] So wildlife pest
control is going to be the work the same
in Riverview as it is in Newport Richie
as it is in everything else because
we're not multiplying the location or
the niche pieces in there. So they'll
all be normalized against themselves if
that makes sense. Like that whole set of
raccoon ones will be worth one uh no
matter what. And then so the Newport
Richie raccoon removal will be worth the
same as um St. Petersburg raccoon
removal because they're the same
pattern, right? Um, so, uh, you'll
notice that those scores look very
similar when you run it just that way
down the list because they are in fact
the exact same calculation happening,
which is why I was kind of hung up. I
was like, is it worth doing that and and
putting them there? But in fact, it it
is because it's easier to audit the
actual math at the end of the day. Um
because we have discrete scores in all
the columns and we can take a sample and
add them up and see if they make sense.
Um because they should, right? Uh so so
that those keyword scores will be pretty
linear set. And then you're going to do
this rank score which is basically just
going to be like this number exists on a
plane from 1 to 10. If it's if it's
worth more than 10, it's it's worth
zero, right? Uh and then we're just
going to apply a very simple curve
analysis, too. We'll have a kappa in
there. So, we can we can make it linear
or we can make it bend really hard, but
we're going to say one is worth this,
two is worth that. And that'll be that
other column, too. And those are all
going to look the same as well because
that should be a flat calculation and
it's irrespective of other calculations,
if that makes sense. And then that last
score is going to take all the other
scores together and factor them. It'll
be this keyword is going to be this
location score times this niche score
times this keyword score times this
ranking score. And the final score is
that. You see what I mean? And then that
final score on all those is the gold
mine because it tells you how much your
rankings are worth
versus assuming what your rankings are
worth. And I can guarant [ __ ] te you
that nobody else has that in their
system. It is a unique novel product
that doesn't exist. And think of it like
this. Not only can you do that for your
company, you can do it for all the
competitors at the same time because you
have that raw response format stuff. So
you can literally see market share by
organic search penetration
on those terms for that you're competing
for. So you know who's your big
competitor and where are they? You can
see when you go into Riverview it's this
guy, but when you go into St. Petersburg
it's this guy.
Who are you fighting against and where
are you fighting them? Very interesting.
The map stuff is similar like the geog
grids, but it doesn't come it doesn't
bring with it the value part, the actual
money.
You know what I mean? That's left as an
assumption. Um, and that's that's I
think the killer piece is like money
times population and then you do your
rank assumption and you're valuing your
service against your other services and
what the market could provide. Am I
targeting the right service, you know?
Um, so there's some some cool [ __ ] to be
found in here uh as we figure this out
because again, like I said, nobody's got
that. um if our if our data for SEO
rankings are accurate. That's like the
big question because they're sort of the
cheapest, right? Um I have no idea how
many credits we're burning through
as we do this. Um but you know, the
cheapest the cheaper your rank tracking,
the better. Um and you may even be able
to uh segment your your keyword plus geo
to a different rank tracker from your
your more important terms. So, as the
keywords become less important, you use
a a cheaper method of researching them,
but the the the really important
keywords you're really rank tracking and
checking because that's it matters to
get those right. So, you might use a
different API um on that one. Uh so,
anyway, this is uh basically what's
going on here. So what what you should
do is you're basically making a series
of distinct scripts, right, that are
going to do different things. The
location one is pretty pretty simple in
the sense that I've already given you a
formula right here. You calculate the
numerical which is this. what is the uh
income minus poverty times population
and then calculate them all sum them
together and then normalize which is
this process and if you say normalize to
the to the AI it's going to understand
what you mean it's a very common term
you're saying I'm looking to calculate a
normalized score of this equation across
this set and it should be able to be
like and then you you calculate that you
write it into the sheet and get all
those normalized scores in there and
then you know sense check them because
you can write the formula yourself right
as well and see if it got it right.
That's called making sure the math
match.
Um so then then doing the same thing uh
with the the service piece is is
important. Um
let's see
that should be straightforward because
services are
or like the niche you're going to have
that data. So you're literally plugging
this in and then you're just doing a
normalization on those, right? So if
you're leaving out rat or whatever
you're not tracking, even though it
might exist in that other sheet and give
you a weird number, you know that these
three numbers added together are going
to equal one when normalized. Right.
Because if you add these all together,
they equal one,
right?
Right. If we did the sum,
yeah, it equals one. See?
So you got to normalize the niche,
normalize the the location calculation.
Then the keyword I've kind of given you
that uh code at least generally. Um so
the trick in that one is going to be
first locating the uh
like dividing these by location and geo
first of all dividing them by service
and then con considering service and geo
as like a bucket that is distinct from
all other buckets and you're calculating
your scores on this and then you have to
figure out which of these are core
keywords and which of them are location
uh keywords, right? Or geo keywords.
Treat them and sort them into their
separate buckets. Calculate their scores
and then look these up again by finding
the service plus the keyword plus geo or
sorry not the service the the geo and
then the keyword geo because you need to
find which wildlife pest control to
write to and then you pop that keyword
score here and they should all be very
similar. It should almost look at like
it repeats. If you compare the Riverview
Raccoon to the Port Newport Richie
raccoon, the numbers should repeat, if
that makes sense. It should be like the
exact same thing. If it's working
correctly. If you see it's not working
correctly and they're different, then
you know that there's a problem in what
you did. Um,
so the keyword score one should be
straightforward. You've got the code
inside that chat GPT. Then you need to
make another formula to calculate the
ranking using you can you can use my
code example on the last one and say hey
we need to make a simplified version of
this where we have a scale of 1 to 10
and we need to make uh a decay curve on
that with a kappa as an input and
anything above 10 should be
automatically zero. Um but one through
10 should be graded on this curve. You
know if it's a kappa of one it's linear.
If it's if it's a decay curve that has a
high kappa then it'll look like that
like a scimitar almost right. Um and so
then you can set the kappa from the
sheet which we did in that config. So
you take the config here uh the keyword
ones there's a there's a a keyword um
split or keyword partition split which
is a zero to one. There's a a keyword um
kappa and then there should be a ranking
kappa. And the ranking cap is what you'd
use in the ranking calculation. Again,
you'll notice that those values seem
very similar to all the other ones. All
the ones will have the same value. All
the twos will have the same value. All
the threes will have the same value
because it's a pretty straightforward
calculation, right? Um and then that
final one is the end of the algo, right?
So I think uh I can give you that
formula now for calculating the final
score if you want. Um, it it's mostly
just multiplication of the different
values, right? Take the Riverview
location score times the raccoon removal
niche score times the keyword score
times the ranking score and you get the
final keyword score. You basically
multiply all the components together,
right?
And then it out and then that's your
score, right? Um, and then from there
you've got an extremely atomic view of
what that keyword ranking has worked to
a client. Uh, the only other way to
enrich that would be to bring in uh
perhaps more competition data uh to the
keyword or um value in jobs based off of
it. Right? A raccoon job is an average
value of this. Uh, you know what I mean?
So that's the only other way to to to
add value. Um
which we could bake in as well. Uh
so yeah,
those are that's basically how it works.
Um so
I I want to kind of sum it up a little
bit more in a mind map. Uh the tasks are
to
create a location um score
script.
Create a
niche score script.
keyword score script.
create a um ranking
score script.
And then finally, you're going to create
a or merge
score scripts
um and factor
uh scores, which is basically going to
be four,
you know. Let's just go back here.
for
wildlife removal as a service in
Riverview for the keyword wildlife pest
control. I'm going to multiply the
keyword score, the ranking modifier
score, the location score, and the niche
score together and get the final score.
You know, it's just multiply, multiply,
multiply, multiply. Um, and then it
should come out to a final score.
Uh and what you'll find is if you were
to have number one rankings across all
terms uh in all markets, if you were to
then add all the final scores together,
they should equal one.
You'll never get that because you're not
getting perfect rankings. But if you
were to have ideal results, they would
average out to one if you added all the
final scores together, if that makes
sense. Um
which would be super cool.
Uh,
so
questions
because this is a lot. I'm kind of
asking you to I I hope I've broken it
down well and I think I solved the
hardest part and given you a script for
it. Um, but I think the keyword part is
going to be hard. I think the the
ranking one will be um
somewhat hard because it's like a weird
calculation but it should be
straightforward too. Uh and you got the
harder version to look at to see you
know to help understand it right. Um so
do you have any questions on it?
Nothing right now. I'll probably have
have to like review this recording.
Yeah. So,
yeah. I expect
review the recording and then, you know,
you can ask me questions over over
Friday, the weekend or whatever. Um, I'd
like to see you writing values to all of
these uh as best you can, right? Um, and
then we can review it kind of Monday.
Probably Tuesday will be the best day to
dive deeper into it because um we got
more time because Monday's got that nine
o'clock. Uh but generally
uh it is somewhat straightforward if you
just think about like take the you know
we've made a new a new sheet so you
don't have to worry about your old
script. You don't have to worry about
integrating with any old code. Um you're
just thinking about writing one script
at a time and dropping the values in and
then adding to it. Okay, now that we've
written the location one, that location
score is still in memory. we've written
it, but now we're going to focus on
writing the niche ones. And then as you
build that script over time, when you
hit the run button, you should be
writing the locations every time and
then the niche every time. And it it
just starts to expand, if that makes
sense. So you go bang bang bang bang
bang bang. And then eventually once
you've done all the keyword and all the
ranking score ones, then the last one is
just go into uh this guy's row, right?
um go for each of these keywords and
calculate the value and put it in.
Calculate the value, put it in,
calculate the value, put it in. That
type of a thing. I'd say avoid at all
cost the need to go reference data from
the script except for at the beginning,
if that makes sense. Um I would load in
at the beginning of the script the
keyword ranking data. Uh basically all
the objects, right? Like you could you
could say um I'm going to
uh pull in my location stuff. I'm going
to pull in my um niche stuff. I'm going
to pull in my keyword rankings. Uh and
then though I'm writing data out, I'm
not ever having to go reference that
written data again to continue my
operation. I'm only writing it out as a
log, right? And that's just so we can
audit it later. Uh, and then that'll
make it easy for us to tell if the the
map does indeed map. Uh, and then if you
if you just kind of follow that
trajectory, you can do keyword last and
do ranking before it, like the actual
ranking score, because that should be
simpler. And then keyword will be the
most complex one. And then at the end,
as long as your your rows match, um, you
should be able to, uh, do the
multiplication very easily, I would
think. Uh, it kind of depends on how you
want to organize your objects, but I
leave that up to you. Um, if you feel
like you can't hack it or whatever and
you're just like, I tried and it totally
screwed up, we obviously know enough
about the problem that I could we could
build the script on the next call and
just try it that way. Um, but I want to
make sure you struggle with it first
because I think that's useful to to
development. So, um, cool. You got the
you got the chat. So, there's the code
in there. Um, yeah. Right on. Good luck
to you.
Um, yeah, don't forget to send me the
recording, Gordon.
Yeah. Yeah. Uh, if you don't see it,
remind me just because, uh, that's taken
a while to process long recordings. So,
yeah, I'll send you a message.
Sounds good. I'll see you later.
See you later, Gordon. Have a good one.
You, too. Byebye.